CHAPTER 7

Consuming and Producing
Feminism through Indian Media
Analysis of Empowerment,
Commodification in Culture Industry

BISWAJIT DAS AND RIDHI KAKKAR

INTRODUCTION

This chapter examines the theoretical grounds of the assumption that empowerment can potentially foster a better portrayal of women through media. During the late 1990s, when popular discourse shifted towards girl power rhetoric, media, and accompanying concepts were deliberately co-related with contemporary ideas on How empowerment can be attained? and, national policies were re-examined to identify perils and paradoxes to promote empowerment. Inspired by the events and the subsequent National Policy for the Empowerment of Women, this paper seeks to examine the notion of empowerment as it corresponds to feminist agency.

Drawing from theoretical viewpoints in both political economy and feminism, this chapter elucidates ‘girl power’ rhetoric as is articulated in popular and feminist discourses. While using the idea of commodification, this paper demonstrates that not all ‘girl power’ rhetoric extends the desired opportunity to women to transcend individual consumption, further, propose collective change in social relations. Even though several feminist literatures are available and offer critique of culture by pin-pointing the body as a site of ideological production; yet this paper demonstrates and emphasizes the need to re-look at the material production of culture. Further, this paper lays together the concepts of agency, empowerment and commodification in subsequent sections. Lastly, this paper demonstrates the farce of the ‘girl power’ rhetoric. With the support of empirical examples, this paper depicts the extent to which the commodified ‘girl power’ rhetoric has distorted feminist notions.

Framing the Issue

A notion emerging out of academic debates and deliberations emphasizes the need of third political liberations, i.e., a liberation from unrepresentative and partisan role of women in India. Formerly, from welfare to development and now from development to empowerment, as argued by scholars and policymakers unanimously, such a departure in the notion of liberation requires transformation from within itself in Indian society. The proceedings of the ‘National Policy for the Empowerment of Women 2001’ states the following:

Within the framework of a democratic polity, our laws, development policies, plans and programmes have aimed at women’s advancement in different spheres … there has been a marked shift in the approach to women’s issues from welfare to development. In recent years, the empowerment of women has been recognized as the central issue in determining the status of women (p. 5).

The said quotation endorses the view of empowerment as central to western democratic theory and practices; in which empowerment is treated as gaining political ability over those who govern. However, in presence of multiple varied terms for ‘development’—it is somehow difficult to reach an agreement or unambiguous statements as of what empowerment in effect entails or how it becomes apparent in an individual, a group or society at any level. Even the academic interventions solely dedicated to scrutinizing the said dimension of development, do not provide comprehensive and uncontested definitions of empowerment. Therefore, we are forced to deduce the meaning of the term ‘development or empowerment’ only from the context of its inclusion in existing literature. As of now, there are two polar views on the ‘empowerment’ of the people in connection with the state.

The first view, as endorsed by the World Bank, visualizes empowerment ‘as a process by which ordinary people, and especially women… take greater responsibility for improving their lives’. Thus, unburdening the state and reducing its role by channelling responsibilities towards citizens. This interpretation reflects the economic point of view of the Bank, where people are expected to be the motor of society and adopt the role of entrepreneurs, rather than the state.

The second extreme view, based on ‘dependency school’, associated with the theories of Paulo Freire (1970), considers ‘empowerment’ as a process meant to enhance people’s abilities to achieve rights, emancipate themselves from dependent economic relations and make endeavours for their just demands on state and its office-bearers.

The former position upholds the dominant modernization view of socio-economic headways. Under the modernization perspective, the economic and social premises of the capitalist market system are looked upon to prepare grounds for achieving equitable development. Advocates of this view promoted that the inequities are the result of flawed application of market principles at specific places or points in time. However, lately, it has been observed by multilateral proponents such as the World Bank and UNDP that specified set of political conditions are also crucial and required for the market to function in a manner, which leads to greater equity. Whereas the latter position puts more emphasis on bringing ‘empowerment’ through changes in social relations, i.e., by expanding the influence or control of the poor and downtrodden over political and bureaucratic systems. However, the pervasive economic order limits the scope of such an outcome to the improvement in the material position only. Therefore, policies revolve around assisting the poor to strengthen their material position within the exigencies of a prevailing market economy.

These varying concepts of ‘empowerment’ not only acknowledge, but also integrate the concept of ‘democratic transformation’ within them. It is through ‘democratic transformation’, that both structural economic reform and political change blend together to make the state more accountable to its citizens. In a nutshell, it suggests the need for attaining required long-term re-arrangements of political and economic relations; thus, ensuring permanent benefits/solutions to the women, instead of mere temporary appropriations within the existing order of things. Before the issue is settled, the recent policy document National Policy for Women: Articulating a Vision for Empowerment of Women 2016, (Draft) highlights

women’s empowerment has been envisaged as a socially inclusive right-based approach while reinforcing the rights and entitlements provided under the ‘Constitution of India’. The policy will enable sustainable socio-economic, political empowerment of women to claim their rights and entitlements, control over resources and formulation of strategic choices in the realization of the principles of gender equality and justice (p. 1).

The shift from empowerment to gender justice is a progressive step ahead. Popular representations and discourses welcomed and popularized the ‘girl power’ across various fields and professions.

Some considered this shift in perspective a progressive step, whereas for others, it was nothing more than mere rhetoric. The results were starting to show up in various activities, be it in work front, education, sports especially, not in traditional girl sports alone but in masculine sports such as hockey, cricket, lawn tennis, and basketball and in popular culture such as in film, music, video and so on. These accomplishments in specific events and fields encouraged the infusion of girl power rhetoric and girls rule paraphernalia that later became part of popular discourse and culture in India.

Scholars in academia as well as among feminist groups, initiated discussions about the ongoing transitions in feminist consciousness and struggling with issues of difference and diversity. While this movement might have encouraged women to be powerful and empowered; the national policy on women promoted a very different type of empowerment of women, contrary from the one being popularized by media and articulated as ‘girl power’. Interestingly, the document of National Policy for Women: Articulating a Vision for Empowerment of Women 2016, (Draft), moves one step ahead by incorporating empowerment within the context of women’s rights. It assumes that the issue of rights would provide access to opportunities, resources, and choices with the freedom of decision-making both within and outside home. Empowerment would be achieved only when advancement in the conditions of women is accompanied by their ability to influence the direction of social change gained through equal opportunities in economic, social, and political spheres of life (p. 1).

Agency and Empowerment

Feminist scholars have written extensively about the issue of ‘agency’, further, those who belong to the field of cultural studies have also made intriguing observations about the ‘agency’. However, within feminist studies the concept of ‘agency’ has been pre-dominantly theorized with women’s resistance, thus, taking no notice of various sorts of independent action at the level of an individual.

Scholars working on women’s studies have incorporated as well as theorized the term ‘empowerment’, whereas the rhetoric of empowerment, in general, is quite common in India’s policy discourse. This is to imply that agency and empowerment might appear coterminous, but for the feminist cultural analysis, the appropriation of empowerment into mainstream popular culture is highly problematic. One of the pressing concerns is that women ‘at the level of individual’ may feel empowered but the same cannot be said for women as a collective body. Thus, a reference from Chantel Mouffe (1979) is worth discussing where she remarked that hegemonic expansion is a by-product of the commodification of empowerment. Following the thought line of Mouffe (1979), this paper argues that the rhetoric of empowerment, instead of challenging power relations meaningfully, does nothing but contributes to rearticulating and recirculating the ever-existing patriarchal and capitalist values. Further, some scholars have also offered novel interpretations to existing understandings of the term ‘empowerment’.

Scholars (Albrecht: 1988; Zimmeraman: 1995) highlight the ability to exert collective influence over the conditions of life or to control one’s own life and destiny can also be deemed as ‘empowerment’. Hence, it is not always that empowerment occurs on the individual level, it can occur at various levels such as interpersonal, professional, organizational, societal, etc. But it is always expected that empowerment at individual level must shape collective behaviour and actions thus leading women to act on remaining levels to challenge and supersede oppressive power relations. Ristock and Pennell (1996) consider empowerment in their work as accessing the means to alter power relations. Empowerment also means creating and evolving new ‘perceptions’ by scholars (see Albrecht: 1988; Chiles and Zorn: 1995). For them, empowerment becomes a part of the reformative approach, i.e., to build and create knowledge that eventually leads the change in the conditions of lives towards betterment, both at individual and collective levels. Jo Rowlands (1997) defines empowerment as a concept that must strive to reverse the top-down hierarchical approach by bringing theories and means of desired social change to praxis. For Rowlands, practical ways can only help people bring changes in the social milieu.

Rowlands (1997) states, that since empowerment can be experienced through the dimensions of personal, relational and collective, it is important to highlight and caution about the risks invoked by such collective actions. She added that as a demerit empowerment or any collective action tends to get carried away with its presupposed meanings, which may drive the people into the ideological trap of ‘right to left’. Just because the term lacks precision in the meaning and is further perplexed by circulation and appropriation in popular discourses; barely there is any scope left for that ‘rhetoric of empowerment’ to inculcate a sense of individual enlightenment and pose a challenge to patriarchal structures. In this situation, chances are higher that the ‘rhetoric of empowerment’ unwittingly adds to individual pretensions rather than attaining some designated goals.

Feminists believe in collective agency, but at the same time, they leave space to exercise individual agency. Thus, they encourage agnostic responses while posing resistance to structural constraints. However, the notion of resistance can be problematic as witnessed by certain subcultural studies (Hebdige: 1979). Further, Schweickart (1995) added that the ‘politics of resistance’ may accentuate individual agency, but in this situation also engulfed in the same debacle as that in ‘empowerment’. Thus, if people behave like individual actors and freely exercise their agency rather than being feminist agents social change may never occur. Moreover, if the notion of resistance presupposes the definition of agency, then there is a possibility of overlooking the importance of material culture shaping social relations. Therefore, Louis Mcnay (2000) problematizes the ambiguity in definition of ‘agency’ and the conundrums of conceptualizing ‘agency’ solely as ‘resistance’. Not to deny the efficacy of all forms of resistance, but it is to suggest that a more precise and varied account of agency is required to explain the differing motivations and ways in which individuals and groups struggle over, appropriate and transform cultural meanings and resources. This, in turn, indicates the necessity of contextualizing agency within power relations in order to understand how acts deemed as resistant may transcend their immediate sphere in order to transform collective behaviours and norms.

Schweickart (1995) stated that the idea of forming a woman collective and at the same time becoming subjected to the collective itself has bothered many feminists. Also, at the same time, a group/ collective cannot be simply carved out and made to work harmoniously from self-interested individuals. Hence, it becomes apparent that if at all ‘agency’ has to be exercised then it certainly cannot be enacted solely at the level of individual or in partisan interests of individuals in particular. Henceforth, Schweickart (1995), asserted a need of a feminist arrangement that acknowledges heterogeneity and diversity of opinion (so as to maintain agency) as well as creates space for collective engagement without undermining or nullifying individual autonomy. This debate of empowerment and agency is inherently challenging and results in a displeasing compromise where women have to choose whether to ‘act’ or to ‘resist’.

‘If at all empowerment stops at the level of individual’, as hypothetically proposed by Ristock and Pennell (1996) and Rowlands (1997) and there is no consciousness beyond that of the individuals solely, then ‘how one can expect transformation in social consciousness and confrontation to social practices that subjugate women?’ Furthermore, Ristock and Pennell (1996) and Rowlands (1997) observed a sudden upsurge in the use of ‘the rhetoric of empowerment’ in popular discourses as well as in women’s self-help literature. Thereby they theorized that the commodification of the idea of ‘empowerment’ has confined the agency to the level of an individual only; thus, restricting any contributions to structural transformations and narrowing the scope of the liberation of women living in patriarchal structures.

The policy document (‘National Policy for the Empowerment of Women 2001’) highlights of the question of media:

… will be used to portray images consistent with human dignity of girls and women. The policy will specifically strive to remove demeaning, degrading and negative conventional stereotypical images of women and violence against women. Private sector partners and media networks will be involved at all levels to ensure equal access for women particularly in the area of information and communication technologies. The Media would be encouraged to develop codes of conduct, professional guidelines and other self-regulatory mechanisms to remove gender stereotypes and promote balanced portrayals of women and men (p. 15).

A closer reading of this paragraph suggests that the policy document highlights:

1. the need for a better image of women through media,

2. participation and access of women in ICT, and finally,

3. to develop guidelines and regulatory mechanisms to remove sex role segregation between men and women.

Although one cannot undermine wishful thinking. However, it does not clarify, how empowerment will be achieved. Or does the fulfilment of the above three objectives lead to empowerment? One is back to square one to the same question of understanding empowerment. While the policy discourse assumes a different meaning of empowerment, the popular discourse reflects the contrary; especially, in entertainment and other popular forms of culture.

The experts have always thought of cultural production and consumption as a reason for the resurgence of the empowerment of women. This further posed a query whether the rise and upsurge of a feminist movement in India should merely be considered as a cultural phenomenon. The answer of this query may be affirmative only if the feminist movement remains within the periphery of philosophical discussion. But if the feminist movement is located within the ‘relations of production’ of burgeoning capitalist society, then feminist philosophy itself becomes political or at least as a politics of representation. Moreover, it entails mass persuasion and publicity, demands for efficiency, productivity, resource allocation, power struggles, cooperations, etc. at the time of their concrete manifestation within the media. All these encompass the domain of the political economy of media. Considering the ever-advancing economy, it has become pertinent to enquire whether varying non-cultural aspects such as economic structures or market forces are hindering the development of feminist values. All this is happening in the face of the increasing prevalence of pluralism. Therefore, it brings the discussion to the question, of whether Indian women will develop their consciousness and form a strong movement; thus, by sweeping the market directions and interests. When the capitalist market is the core subject, even then it is given a pejorative meaning, whenever analysed with culture. While growing up in a tech-abundant age, many Indian women have started using electronic gadgets and the internet, besides other forms of mass media-produced consumer culture. Thus, ‘commodification’ offers a point of entry from where such social relations can be examined. ‘Commodification’, illustrates the differences between the portrayals in popular culture and the empowerment of women; and how these become conflated.

The process of commodification is important as well as two-folded in the field of communication. It enables media commodities to produce surplus value for the owners as well as frame and shape the consciousness of the audience’s minds while circulating the ideological meaning. Considering the duality of cultural commodities, Meehan (1994) suggests ‘one must rethink media commodities as both culture industry and industrial culture’ (p. 564) as cultural commodities comprise both social relations and ideological meanings. Dallas Smythe (1978) too has written significantly about the process of commodification suggesting that the process turns the ‘audience’ to mere commodity of media. Smythe’s argument brings into the picture the linkages between media content, advertisers and audience in turning the audience into a commodity. Further, Mosco (1996) terms ‘a set of binding reciprocal relationships’ whereby media companies construct audiences through programming and advertisers pay for access to audiences (p. 148). Hence, the audience as a commodity is manufactured and sold by media to corporations. Symthe’s contribution has widened the horizon of commodity production beyond the periphery of media, i.e., newspapers, magazines, television, films, etc.; thus, portraying how the rhetoric of empowerment is being used and drawing in the claim of the audience.

Girl Power and the Cultural Production

Cultural production of ‘girl power’ takes in the form of music, film, art, via the internet, club culture, etc. These messages are overtly political, and many girls with a girl power sensibility engage in activism via their cultural production. The women involved in these nebulous movements distrust conventional politics. They evade any media-given labels and publicly denounce attempts to gather their divergent work into the ambit one single category. Many of the women involved in the early stages of the movement are college-educated and well-versed to some extent in feminist theory. Which partly forms the basis for their feminist consciousness. Some common themes that emerge, centre on girls controlling their cultural production. Women become courageous to take action against constraining patriarchal capitalist institutions by getting inspired by the radical messages. Before computers became popular among the masses and became widely accessible to the Indian middle class, people used to make collages out of magazines, newspapers, etc. and arrange printed words and pictures into new contexts and new meanings. Even after the arrival of computers and sophisticated printing solutions that have made production and distribution easier, artists still admire the non-professional old rustic look. This aesthetic adds credibility to and promotes their critique of hegemonic structures and contributes to the emotion of a genuine rebellion against the status quo of professionalization. While the circulation of such materials helps expand this feminist network; further, the internet enables the fostering a dynamic movement. These materials, through the internet, are circulated, distributed, and connected across the globe and the websites are turning into e-zines with inspiring essays and engrossing trending discussions. The internet promoted ‘girl power’ and supported to building and maintaining a network community of girls. Several websites circulated information about feminist gatherings such as time, date and locations for meetings and other events. Most of the websites also included some sort of ‘mission statements’ that propose and promote the feminist objectives in general as well as a person’s interpretation of the subject. The understanding promoted by these websites of third-wave feminism sets the grounds for second-wave feminist’s critique of overarching social structures, including ideas, power and subjectivity as envisioned in postmodern feminism.

Even though the discussion above celebrates ‘girl power’ cultural production; it is important to recognize that the material and art loaded with ‘girl power’ message are also commodified and structured by the constraints of exchange value, thereby feminist content on the women portals and internet are also organized within the constraints of capitalism. However, the semi-independent production and distribution network at least promotes a feminist message which is inherently different from the typical ‘girl power’ rhetoric being produced and circulated through popular culture. These motivated organizations as groups work as collectives, therefore, artists have more say and authority over operations. Their work, ideas, narratives, visions, political messages, etc. are not compromised, and their labour is not solely governed by profit motives. Amid the discussion above one cannot rule out the nature of exchange value and oppressive patterns of production and distribution following a capitalist model; even then one can suggest with conviction that this alternative process has somehow challenged the patriarchal and capitalist structures.

Commodifying Girl Power

Even though ‘girl power’ as a social movement refrained from any associations with commodification but idea of women’s empowerment could not be able to elude itself from getting commodified. Cultural products such as music, videos, films, magazines, etc. have promoted and popularized the notion of ‘girl power’ and encouraged society members to value girls and prioritize their needs and issues. This follows the logic that if society starts to value girls, then, in return girls will also feel optimistic and empowered. The idea of ‘girl power’ is notable, but has been reified into tangible commodities bought and sold by entertainment corporations in the form of music, soap opera, films, etc. These evident examples of popular culture portray how use value, the notion of empowering girls has eventually changed into exchange value. Thus, the commodities which are aimed for empowering girls in a process of transformation have lost their original meaning and essence. This diluted meaning of girl power has been rearticulated in a number of ways to appeal to the masses. Therefore, feminists criticize the ideologically contradictory meanings embedded in popular culture by revealing how contradictory textual meanings dominate the largest audiences for profit purposes. Most evident of them are women related soaps running on prime-time slots, advertisements, films, music videos, etc. These are the products of the most notorious mainstream projections of feminism, loaded with themes and misleading messages of woman empowerment.

As Ipshita Chanda (2000) rightly points out,

Television ads are seductively defining the persona of the modern woman, an entity that we, within the women’s movement cannot ignore. And it is because of this seductive through ambiguous projection that we find, echoes of a familiar rhetoric popularized by the struggles of the women’s movement, being appropriated in the service of systems and structures that these struggles were and are being waged against. The meanings of words like rights, equality, freedom or even empowerment seem to be sliding out of our control and even beyond our comprehension (p. 42).

In the television films advertisements or any other fiction, men play the role of the dominant protagonist, the whole fictional narrative revolves around them, they are treated as masters; while women are always given side roles as their supporters, admirers, caretakers and entertainers not more than a prop in a narrative (Behera: 1989).

Similarly, the women-oriented serials highlight anti-women images. The heroine miraculously overcomes her repression and mouths a few sentences about her power and independence (Choudhury: 1987). Most of these serials construct Masculine and Feminine genders as opposites. A few heroic women are shown but cast as redeemers of patriarchy. The trend to commercialization creates new contradictions (Krishnan and Dighe: 1990).

The films in India reflect diverse views of the empowerment of women. Although, occasionally, they posit a conflict between modern feminism and traditional values, however, in the last analysis they surrender to the age-old patriarchal values. Popular songs of the films pose women as intoxicating objects and serve as erotic objects. Invariably, the songs are showcased much before the release of films and work as an advert for the films. The constant repeat of these songs makes the viewers a nation of voyeurs. The song sequence does not serve only to present the female body as a spectacle. Indeed, song sequences are choreographed with movements which simulate sexual intercourse. Invariably, in these sexual postures, the image of the male being the dominant one and the woman as the receptacle who must be seen to be enjoying what is being done to her. Popular Hindi cinema as well as TV series, promotes unrealistic images of women through an archaic set of values. The celluloid place of women is always lower or lesser than the male hero. The male is projected as an active decision-maker of the house while the female as someone living at the mercy of the male heads of the family. This represents the depending on the image of women that has proven to be a hurdle for the feminist movement in India. But due to some serious and dedicated efforts of some committed individuals the image of women started evolving from being a mere social and domestic necessity. Thus, this turns Indian cinema into a battleground for gender wars, with women not ever standing up to supremacy.

Rao (1989) studied changing versions of femininity over 75-years in mainstream as well as so-called art films in India. She captures aptly in her study the images of women: a shift from goddesses to dream girls to the new woman. The female characters in the movies are used to portray the conventional structures of a patriarchal society. In defense the filmmakers of the industry stated that women in films are not degraded rather in a few instances they are stereotyped (Bagchi: 1996). Further, Bagchi comments that although there are exceptions such as films like Mother India, Bandini, Sujata, Arth, Aradhana, Anupama, Mili, Aandhi and Ankur invariably, most of the successful films of yester years show that female characters promote the legend that popular icons are women who have no ambitions or interest beyond dressing up to the nines for their beloveds, or stepping out of their four walls once they’ve ensnared their spouses and who derive joy and pride from serving in-laws, looking after their precocious children and queening over the kitchen a la Biwi No. 1 (Bagchi: 1996).

The new generation of filmmakers is no way exception to it except catering to the market by reinforcing the stereotypes. Bagchi analyses that a film like Dushman, a story based on women’s empowerment ultimately takes recourse to male support to achieve desired results. Rarely, do women actresses have a voice to question their roles, although a few exceptions are there.

While the film portrays women in a conservative role, recent music videos have added a considerable amount of sensation to the Indian cultural scenario. Although there are opposition by the larger society to some extent but music-videos with their remix and dance sequences brought to the limelight another conception of women. This shift can be viewed from passive, exploited, oppressed to active, exploiting and oppressing the other. The woman is shown in skimpy dresses wearing full-on make-up, and a lot of body adornments, etc. to enhance the sexual appeal. The messages which are being conveyed through these ‘item-songs or dance numbers’ are highly distorted and suggest that the empowerment of women means vulgarity, overt sexuality, and temptation for the male gaze. Also, the lyrics of the song and nature of body gestures are created in a manner which portrays that girls can only achieve power and empowerment by using their sexuality and looks.

Since time immemorial, society has a perception that women gain access to power through their sexuality and appearance. Even their whims and fancies are considered an ornament of sexuality. Women’s intelligence and skills are never given due recognition. Thus, women are considered whimsical and media representations are products as well as manifest evidence of this prejudice. These messages are not new, through out 1970s-80s second-wave feminists have countered them. In continuation of second-wave feminism, third-wave feminism depicts efforts towards degendering of the body. They redefined the notion of beauty and sexuality. But, if television ‘soaps’ turned towards a more conservative-impractical appearance/outlook of women to adorn the male gaze; then the music videos in the name of subverting the patriarchal gaze, capitalized the women’s bodies by the voluptuous portrayal of female beauty. Music videos were not celebrating all types of women’s bodies such as fat, one-breasted, short, hippy, dark and so on rather, in due process they are reinscribing the socially acceptable benchmarks and institutionally set body types.

Even though media content celebrates make-up, beauty, clothes and other aspects of girl culture they don’t question or rather hide that the girls are not free to choose, or they lack the agency to freely make choices. Females are socialized in a manner which doesn’t give them direct access to economic or political power. Patriarchal society is structured in a manner that doesn’t permit women to exercise agency without seeking male’s approval. Therefore, media content primarily served as the indirect means of accessing the empowerment of women. If females being the active consumer of media content take charge of their beauty and sexuality, even then they become subservient to the male gaze. Thereby, women should be encouraged to develop means to acquire power by becoming independent and vocal about their needs rather than adhering to the material culture promoted by media content.

Many feminists believe that the media doesn’t perceive patriarchal institutions as a real threat. Media instead of challenging the status quo, uses the status quo to generate favourable attention and profit. Media neither suggest any alternative for women’s empowerment nor encourages them to seek political or economic power. While celebrating girl culture, media organizations mask patriarchal and capitalist structures and pave the way for oppressive behaviours. Therefore, when the media content highlights and standardizes female beauty and body types with accompanying messages of empowerment then they indeed trying to sell their pro-girl artefacts—commodified feminism.

Third-wave feminism is different from the brand of feminism posed by the music videos because it not only recognizes feminist body politics but also pays attention to structural forces such as patriarchy and capitalism that add on to the constraints on women. While third-wave feminist asserts their sexuality, it is not necessarily for the male gaze shall change. Girls shall be treated as both subject and object of the male gaze. The third-wave of feminism redefined sexuality by encouraging girls to take pleasure in their bodies, like themselves no matter what size, shape, or colour. Also, it contributed hugely to debunking notions such as racism, sexism, homophobia, heterosexualism, fatism, ageism, etc. and accompanying injustices with it. Although third-wave feminism never intended to be commodified, certain aspects no matter what got transferred into commodities, such as the notion of girl power.

One of the drawbacks of girl power commodification is the symbolic exclusion of elderly or older age women as ‘soap series’ leads. Several TV producers accepted that to target the mainstream audience which has developed a liking for young women as well as most of the advertisers, they prefer to cast younger women in the roles. This not only depicts the change in demographics but also exposes the falseness of TV programmes messages about socially just society for women. Like any other industry, the media industry too follows the dictum of revenue.

The internet and its accessibility have grown greatly, it has become more interactive as well as much more commercial. It encouraged several young women with similar views and opinions to connect. While capitalizing on the girl power rhetoric, several advertiser-driven platforms and services on the internet have developed. These platforms are then sold to advertisers.

While closely examining the matter, one shall find that more emphasis is being laid on expanding the domain of duties and responsibilities of the females, rather than reclaiming the ‘rights’, to keep patriarchy and male domination intact (CAR: 2007, 187).

For instance, in the plot of the TV serial Kahani Ghar Ghar Ki, a blind girl is being raped by two male members of the family. Daughters-in-law, the protagonist of the show, who is depicted as very bold, independent, and mighty fights for justice for that girl (victim of rape), while going against the will of her husband and the family. The mother-in-law applauds her daughter-in-law for her intentions to seek justice for the rape victim, but at the same time reminds her about her duty to preserve the honour of the family. Thus, Maaji (mother-in-law) proclaims that the daughters-in-law (female protagonist) must bring her husband back on the right path and try to arbitrate the issue within the domain of family itself, instead of taking the issue of domestic violence to court (CAR: 2007)

TV serials, thus assume that this process of re-affirming ‘responsibilities’ rather than ‘rights’ for women shall have a much better reception among women viewers. The popularity of these TV shows amongst a cross-section of viewers indicates, how much they cater to the emotional and psychological needs of woman viewers and alter the audience’s perspective with twists and turns in the plot lines. Therefore, these shows promote manipulation of the idea of empowerment and are considered highly regressive by those working for women’s empowerment.

The much popularity of these TV shows comes from the way the family is displayed. The family is shown at the conjecture of tradition and modernity, thereby striving to maintain its traditional values as well as legacies and at the same time facing the challenges of modernity. The only common thing is the ‘state of flux’ in every plot.

The TV drama series displays immense faith in the traditional values of the Indian family system and gives due preference to them in multiple renewing ways, i.e., through dress code to extravagant celebrations of festivals and rituals. Other than these overt performances, traditional values are re-asserted in subtle ways through dialogues and discourses in plots of conflicts and disagreements. These plots are gender biases against women, thus raising serious questions on the so-called claims of pro-women representation of these serials. All the claims of modernity and change are farce because the screenplay and the storyline of the show reassert that tradition is more suited to the persona and needs of Indian women and modernity adds to negative character of vulgarity and disgrace to overall women’s personality. At last, it is stressed that ‘right’ kind of change can only come through the reinvention of the tradition.

This ‘right’ kind of change approach is highly problematic. The ‘change’ is packaged and presented in a way, that suggest that family set-up is deeply under threat in modern times, therefore women must not cross the limits set by traditional values. If women cross the line of family, then her return shall be guided by process of agnipariksha (purity test to prove her chastity) and vanavasa (exile/separation to repent of the deeds) (based on Ramayana mythology). Therefore, women must not take extreme steps and strife for change within the domestic limits by solely bearing all pain and sacrifices.

Hence, it is important to unravel this ‘process of packaging the change’, which represents the mode of transition or change ‘through re-establishing the traditional family with all its gender and power constructs’.

Further, the female characters in most of these TV shows manifest throughout the course of show how the husband’s family and house should be maintained. Parvati the protagonist of Kahani Ghar Ghar Ki, is a perfect wife, daughter-in-law, mother, sister-in-law, etc. She is a care giver to extended family and thrives to restore the values of the family threatened by other family members or the antagonist character of the show.

TV serials proactively display superficial attitudes towards women. Female characters are portrayed as authoritative, kind, ferocious and sometimes conniving, but never overtly submissive. Despite all the assertions, female characters are shown promoting traditional trappings, from dressing to mannerisms, from observing rituals to following day-to-day protocols, etc., which are all part of the packaging strategy. Thus, one can observe the return to gender characterization along the lines of predominant stereotypes of males and females.

Most of the scenes are shot in sets of kitchens, bedrooms, living rooms, etc. spaces that are within the perimeter of the house only, reasserting the stereotypical geographical boundaries of women. Further, women are shown outside the home only when there is trouble with her spouse or family members. Thus, these shows insist on the depiction of almost every aspect of life mainly in terms of the family, thereby, preventing gender from being explored in the modern context.

There can be no engagement with viewers’ response, and no critique of content shall prove useful unless we question the process of packaging content and unravel what viewers are expecting from the producers of this content. Deconstruction of situational context is more needed than storyboard, to decode the contextual structure of these family shows and to use TV medium as the measure for raising issues on gender rights.

CONCLUSION

This paper argues for an examination of the rhetoric of feminist empowerment. We suggest that there are serious implications for the popularization of the term empowerment and this needs to be situated in a discussion of feminist agency. While individual empowerment in women can help foster collective agency, it more often has the effect of stunting women, encouraging them to work only for themselves in the immediate moment. This of course is far from women working collectively as individuals toward significant structural changes that will help improve the lives of others. Without a doubt, it is necessary for women to feel some sort of power, but as this article suggests, when it is commodified, empowerment can come at the expense of actual change.

We need a definition of feminism that clarifies and articulates our sense of feminism as a movement whose coherence hinges on the heterogeneity of its constituents, and whose stability and durability depend on its capacity for revision and development. Third-wave feminism allows for this, yet within its multiple articulations, women must distinguish between what is a feminist project originating from feminist roots and what is feminist rhetoric being packaged and sold by media industries and bought by many young women. A cultural analysis informed by political economy, in this case commodification, illustrates how cultural production can be a part of feminist projects for social change. If empowerment stops at an individual level, it does just that, serves the individual. If this is the case, women will be forever reproducing social relations that are rooted in patriarchal oppression and capitalist exploitation.

The conclusion drawn manifests that ‘national policy’ would be unlikely to hasten the process of empowerment until the political concept of empowerment is given a central prominence to the activities. Therefore, government intervention must conspicuously include strategies informed by the political evolution of women’s issues and the role of mass media in India.

REFERENCES

Albrecht, Terrance L. (1988). ‘Communication and Control in Empowering Organization’, Annals of the International Communication Association vol. 11, no. 1: 380-90.

Bagchi, Amitabha (1996). ‘Women in Indian Cinema’. Retrieved 12 August 2002, from http://www.cs.jhu.edu/~bagchi/women.html

Behera, Sunil K. (1989). ‘Gender Role Biases on Indian Television’, Media Asia, vol. 16, no. 3, 119-24.

Centre for Advocacy and Research (2007). ‘Packaging the Contemporary Woman in Television Fiction: Deconstructing the Role of “Commerce” and “Tradition”’, In Ghadially, R., Urban Women in Contemporary India—A Reader.

Carter, Kathryn and Carole Spitzack (eds.) (1989). Doing Research on Women’s Communication: Perspectives on Theory and Method, Norwood, New Jersey, ablex.

Chanda, Ipshita (2000). ‘Displaying the modern Women: Feminism in the Labyrinths of Media Culture’, in Social Scientist, vol. 28, nos. 3-4, March-April, 40-60.

Chaudhury, Manisha (1987). ‘Images of Women through Television’, Communicator, 29-31.

Chiles, A.M. and Zorn, T.E. (1995). ‘Empowerment in Organizations Employees Perception of the Influences on Empowerment’, Journal of Applied Communication Research, 23: 1-25.

Freire, Paulo (1970). Pedagogy of the Oppressed, New York: Seabury Press.

Gallagher, Margaret (1989). ‘A Feminist Paradigm for Communication Research’, in Brenda Dervin, Lawrence Grossberg et al. (eds.), Rethinking Communication: Paradigm Exemplars, London: Sage Publications.

Hebdige, Dick (1979). Subculture: The Meaning of Style. London: Methuen.

Kaplan, E. Ann (1987). ‘Feminist Criticism and Television’, in Channels of Discourse: Television and Contemporary Criticism. London, Methuen.

Krishnan, P. and Dighe, A. (1990). Affirmation and Denial: Construction of Femininity on Indian Television. New Delhi: Sage.

Mcnay, Louis (2000). Gender and Agency Reconfiguring the Subject in Feminist and Social Theory. Malden. MA: Polity.

Meehan, Eileen R. (1994). ‘Conceptualizing Culture as Commodity: The Problem with Television’, in Horace Newcomb (ed.), Television: The Critical View, New York: Oxford University Press.

Mosco, Vincent (1996). The Political Economy of Communication, London: Sage Publications.

Mouffe, Chantel (1979). Hegemony and Ideology in Gramsci. Gramsci and Marxist Theory. Routledge, London, pp. 182-3.

National Policy for the Empowerment of Women (2001). Department of Women and Child Development. Ministry of Human Resource Development, Government of India.

National Policy for Women: Articulating a Vision for Empowerment of Women (2016). Draft, Ministry of Women and Child Development. Government of India.

Rao, Leela (1989). ‘Woman in Indian Films: A Paradigm of Continuity and Change’, Media, Culture and Society, vol. 11, no. 4, 443-58.

Ristock, Janice L. and Joan Pennell (1996). Community Research as Empowerment: Feminist Links, Postmodern Interruptions, Toronto: Oxford University Press.

Rowlands, Jo (1997). Questioning Empowerment: Working with Women in Honduras, Dublin: Oxfam.

Schweickart, Patrocinion P. (1995). What are we doing? What do we want? Who are we? Comprehending the Subject of Feminism. In Judith Kegan Gardiner (ed.), Provoking Agents Gender and Agency in Theory and Practice, Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 229-48.

Smythe, Dallas (1978). ‘Communications: Blindspot of Western Marxism’, Canadian Journal of Political and Social Theory, 1(3): 1-27.

Vanzoonen, Liesbet (1991). ‘Feminist Perspectives on the Media’, in James Curran and Michael Gurevitch (eds.), Mass Media and Society. London: Edward Arnold.

Zimmeraman, Marc A. (1995). ‘Psychological Empowerment: Issues and Illustrations’, American Journal of Community Psychology, 23(5): 581-99.